It seems to me that from those sanctions that were
Мне кажется что из тех санкций которые
imposed on Russia from the fourteenth and
наложили на России с четырнадцатого а
then from the twentieth of the second Yes, not everything is so
потом с дца второго Да не всё так уже
rosy. What dynamics look at
радужно стоит Какая динамика Посмотрите
the dynamics of prices and the dynamics of wages in general, it’s
динамику цен и динамику зарплат вообще
unpleasant, on the contrary, by the way, by the
неприятно правда наоборот кстати кстати
way, that’s why inflation is now accelerating
вот у нас поэтому сейчас разгоняется
in our country, that our wage dynamics  higher
инфляцию что у нас динамика зарплат выше
than the price dynamics so now Wow
чем динамика цен поэтому сейчас Вау
seriously
серьёзно Здравствуйте
Hello Hello something Speak very quietly
Здравствуйте что-то Очень тихо
let's get louder Hello
говорите давайте погромче Здравствуйте
beaz And what kind of enthusiasm should I have
беаз А какой меня должен быть энтузиазм
Well, somehow inspire me into a conversation
Ну как-то вот воодушевить в разговор
there you yourself are
там вы сами
from where I am from the Nizhny Novgorod region Arzamas
откуда я с Нижегородской области Арзамас
where I am from Rostov myself But  I’ve
откуда Я сам родом из Ростова Но 18 лет
been living in California for 18 years, in a year it will be like this
живу в Калифорнии через года будет дто
[music]
[музыка]
What are you talking about
О чём общаетесь
here, I don’t know how it will turn out, I’m interested in
тут не знаю как получится интересуюсь
how people live, what they think about, and how they
как люди живут о чём думают ещё как
live, what I think about. Well, it depends differently on
живут о чём думаю Ну по-разному смотря
where. Well, how is it there in the Nizhny Novgorod
где Ну как у вас там в Нижегородской
region? How are the prices there?
области Как там цены
salaries Well, how normal by our
зарплаты Ну как нормально по нашим
standards is
меркам
normal S M
нормально С М
Swa Depends on what you compare it to,
Сва Смотря с чем сравнивать
how everything is relative if you compare it with the
как всё относительно если сравнить там с
standard of living there, for example in
уровнем жизни например в
California. Well, I don’t know what your
Калифорнии Ну я не знаю какой у вас
standard of living is there. Well, for example,
уровень жизни там не жи Ну вот например
I’m a university teacher, I have a
Я преподаватель университета У меня
small salary of 9000  dollars a month
небольшая зарплата 9000 долларов в месяц
is not a lot
это небольшая
You
У вас
Kaya I have, well, if you translate yours Well,
Кая у меня ну если вашу перевести Ну по
probably it will work out like this, but how do you
наверно г так получится а как вы
survive normally I survive
выживает нормально выживаю
what can you buy at all
что вообще можно на по
I
купить Я нормально
survive normally I have
выживаю у меня он
one foreign car in my fatherland such non-
отечестве иномарка одна такие не
luxury cars
люксовые автомобили
one 000 dollars how do you like it  products
оди 000 долла как вам продукты
communal apartment Well, communal apartment Well, I
коммуналка Ну коммуналка Ну у меня у нас
probably know how much you have for
наверно знае там сколько у вас
communal apartments, we have communal apartments, so I
коммуналка у нас коммуналка вот я
’ll pay for communal apartments, how much it
поплачу коммуналку сколько у меня
costs me, well, probably it comes out per
выходит ну тып наверное выходит в
month Damn, how do you survive there, I
месяц Блин как вы выживает там я вообще
don’t
не
know at all Yes, it’s okay, at least I’m not complaining  I
знаю Да нормально Не жалуемся я по
’m not complaining Well, in Russia
крайней мере не жалуюсь Ну так в России
no one complains in Russia you can’t
никто не жалуется в России нельзя
complain Why Whoever complains gets
жаловаться Почему Кто жалуется того
jailed Complains Well, who said that,
садят жалуется Ну кто он так сказал у
we have full knowledge that we wouldn’t have enough prisons
нас полно знаете тюрем бы не хватило
How many people seriously complain in
Сколько народу жалуется у
Russia Yes, there are always enough prisons in Russia,
серьёзно Да тюрем России всегда хватит у
I have a classmate who also complained to
меня он одноклассник тоже пожаловался
the governor  sat
губернатору сел
down Yeah, sat down, sat down What do you think, what do you think, how
Угу сел сел Как вы думаете а вам по
many
вашему там как это много у нас
prisoners do we have in
заключённых в
Russia? I think yes,
России я думаю да
but you can look at
а посмотреть можете
the statistics.
статистику
Why, for the sake of interest? Look at
Зачем ради интереса Посмотрите
the statistics, we are talking about political
статистику горим про политических
prisoners who
заключённых политически которым что-то
don’t like something politically, and not about criminals here in
не нравится а не про уголовников вот в
Russia  just in America, criminals
России как раз в Америке уголовники
are in prison in Russia, they are in power,
сидят в тюрьме в России сидят при власти
that’s the
вот в чем
problem prodi
проблема проди
Well, when you asked Yes, I’ll answer you
Ну когда вы спросили Да тебе отвечу я
when I lived in Rostov. I thought about it when
когда жил в Ростове Я про подумал когда
I came to California, I realized how they
я приехал в Калифорнию я понял как нас
deceived us and became a
обманывали и стал
propagandist, now they’ve been
пропагандистом теперь
propagandizing for 18 years  as he left, he didn’t
пропагандируют 18 лет как уехал то не
come. My father came to see me in
приезжал Отец мой приезжал ко мне в
California, but I didn’t come to Russia,
Калифорнию но я в Россию не
what did he say there, they grab everyone,
приезжал что он там сказал всех хватают
arrest them on the street, and as he said
арестовывают на улице м как сказа он
a little, he’s behind Putin with me. Well, I
немножко это он за Путине с у меня Ну я
tell him, his pension is 20,000 rubles, yes
ему говорю у него пенсия 20.000 руб да
that’s it.  21 something In short, in our opinion it
это 21 с чем-то Короче это по-нашему
turns out to be about 210 dollars I say
получается где-то 210 долларов я говорю
dad, uh, what did this state give you,
батя ээ что тебе дало это государство
it ripped you off and didn’t give you anything That’s what
оно ободрала тебя и не дала ищё Вот что
you can tell my dad
вы моему бате можете сказать
Why he has a
Почему у него
pension I don’t
пенсия не
know the person in Russia who gave it  all his
знаю человек в России который отдал всю
life in his Motherland Yes, there he worked at a
жизнь Родине Да там он работал на
factory receiving a salary of 21,000 rubles Oh, not a
заводе получая 21000 руб зарплаты Ой не
salary pension
зарплата пенсии
Why why in Russia there are such small
чему Почему в России вот такие маленькие
salaries oh pensions
зарплаты ой пенсии
oil gas diamonds they are very rich
нефть газ алмазы они очень богатые
Why how much
Почему сколько у нас
oil gas do we need, they don’t just need them They
нефти газа их же надо не просто Они же
lie there Not just  they are lying sluggishly vulgar for sale
лежат Не просто же лежат вял пошл прода
it turns out that Russia was selling gas to the whole of
получается что Россия продавала во всю
Europe Yes, some small Czech Republic
Европу газ Да какая-то маленькая Чехия
there Hungary Estonia Latvia bought gas
там Венгрия Эстония Латвия покупали газ
from Russia and Russia lived poorer than them why
у России и Россия жила беднее их почему
so
так
about whom the
про кого прове
Czechs were talking about I don’t know whether they were richer or poorer but the
чехи Я не знаю богаче или беднее но е
Czechs I was well  they don’t live much richer there
чехи я был ну там не особо-то они богаче
Well, if we look
живут Ну если мы смотрим
Yes, the salaries of the Czech Republic are the salaries of Russia and from
Да зарплаты Чехии зарплаты России и из
Russia to the Czech Republic again Look, this is all the bass
России в чеи ещ раз Смотри это все бас
from Russia in the
из России в
Czech Republic in
че из Чехии в
Russia has already left for the Czech Republic to live I was just
России уехал уже в Чехию жить Я просто
visiting and
посещал
watching
смотрел
That I have nothing  I had no
Что Ничего нет у меня не было у меня
desire to stay there to live in the
желания остаться там жить в
Czech Republic Well, yes, but people from Russia
Чехии Ну да Но люди из России в Чехию
come to the Czech Republic for permanent residence And from the Czech Republic to Russia
Приезжают на ПМЖ А из Чехии в России
for some reason No why Well, I don’t know With
почему-то Нет почему Ну я не знаю С
such statistics, how many people
такой статистики приезжают сколько там
come here and there people go, you
приезжают туда-сюда люди ездят
know, look  statistics are leaving,
знаете мо посмотреть статистику уезжает
here's the salary, here's the interest Just Google the
вот зарплата вот интерес Просто в Гугле
teacher's salary in your city So I'm
зарплата учителя в вашем городе Вот мне
wondering again how the city is in the
интересно ещё раз как город в
Nizhny Novgorod
Нижегородской
region Well, here under Nizhny thunder I'm still
области Ну тут под Нижним гром я все
lying in a village near Nizhny but in the village Well, the
лежу в деревне под Нижним но деревне Ну
district
район как райцентр
is called the district center Kstovsky district
называется Кстовский район
Kstovsky Yeah, now I'll take a look  I haven’t
Кстовский Угу сейчас я посмотрю я не
even heard that this is the city of Kstov or
слышал Даже тако это город кстова или
what it’s called dadada yes absolutely
как оно называется дадада да совершенно
interesting it’s cool what does that
верно интересно прикольно а что это
mean
означает
beds No idea how to be honest
коек Без понятия как честно говоря
right now
сечас
Kstovsky
Кстовский
so
так зарплата
teacher’s salary Yes
учителя Да статистика
salary statistics for 2024 the average
зарплат за 2024 год средняя зарплата
teacher’s salary in Kstovo for 2024 is
учителя в кстове за 2024 год
rubles then  you're sweating something I
руб то уж что-то вы поте Я за городработ
immediately gave me a job for the city Well, well, now let's
сразу мне выдал А ну ну давайте сейчас
look at another site shows another 19
посмотрим другой сайт показывает ещё 19
Well, look, it's real, I
Ну посмотрите это реально я вот так и
typed it in like this Yes, in Google, a teacher's salary is
вбил Да в Гугле зарплата учителя к
100 median
100 медианная
19.2 average
19.2 средняя
22.22 so
22.22 так
where are you looking at the doc?
а вы где смотрите доком
Gorodrabot ru
сходите городработ ру
issued it like this Well, I don’t know, I have
выдала так Ну да не знаю у меня вот
a friend, my wife has a friend. She
Учите знакомая есть у жены Она где-то
gets a teacher somewhere around 6. You
около 6 получает учитель е ещ раз Вы
saw saw
видели видели
yes Well, maybe I don’t know
да Ну может быть не знаю
Yes, but I don’t think what kind of e even in the heel of
Да но я не думаю что за е даже в пятке
some kind  Well,
какой-то са
I typed it and you checked it Yes,
я вот набрал и вы же это проверили Да
it’s not Well, it might be, you know, it
это не Ну это может быть это знаете
might not be a salary, it might be a salary,
может не зарплата это может быть оклад
that’s the same, they have a salary, that’s a
такой там же у них учи оклад это есть
rate, wait, well, if he works
ставка подожди Ну да если он работает в
twice as hard, of course he’ll get
два раза больше Конечно будет получать в
double  times more, but you have to work
два раза больше но это пахать надо в два
twice as many
раза больше
hours, they have one pay rate there, 4 hours, and
часов у них там одна ставка 4 часа е раз
look, we see teach,
смотри мы см учи
there is a teacher I know, yes, she
есть знакомая учительница да она
gets paid. She works there for about two
получает Она работает там где-то на две
or one and a half times the pay rate, she doesn’t work for
или полторы ставки она же не работает
24 hours, she works 8  hours then there
сутки работает-то 8 часов потом там у
they have additional payments there there are additional payments there for experience there are additional payments
них там доплаты есть там за стаж доплаты
there for qualifications there are additional payments then I
там за квалификацию доплаты потом я
understand correctly this management is a great
понимаю это руководство классное
management that cla you are in charge of that
руководство что кла руководите того
everything she
всего у неё чистыми
gets clean e times means Look when you
получается е раз значит Смотри когда вы
say that she works for two pay rates
говорите что она работает на две ставки
Yes this is a person who works  on two jobs it’s
Да это человек работает на двух работах
called
называется
Pravda Well, well, she understands They have One
Правда Ну ну она же понимаете У них Одна
hundred you understand They have One rate Once
ста понимаете У них Одна ставка Ещё ещё
again 4 hours a day 4 hours a day work
раз 4 часа в день 4 часа в день работа
understand once again for some reason once again for
понима ещё раз почему-то ещё раз
some reason uh teachers Yes they give exactly
почему-то э учителям Да дают именно
this load because  that according to the standards
такую нагрузку потому что по нормативам
Yes, a person can report so much plus
Да человек может отчитать столько плюс
he must also prepare for these
он должен ещё подготовиться к этим
lessons, he must then check the notebooks
урокам он должен потом проверить тетради
and so on, yes, that is, 4 hours a day -
и так дальше да то есть 4 часа в день -
These are only lecture classes, that is,
Это только лекционных занятий то есть
class lessons, so besides this, his
классных уроков так Кроме этого у него у
teacher has so many more  tasks Yes,
учителя есть ещё столько задач Да
which he does outside is great,
которые он делает вне классно получается
so the question is, if two wages, this is
так вот вопрос если две ставки это ж по
essentially a person working two jobs,
сути человек работает на двух работах
true Yeah, yes, that is, we don’t
правда Угу да то есть это мы же не
evaluate How much a person will receive if
оцениваем Сколько человек получит если
he works five jobs, six
он будет работать на пяти работах шести
we look at One job, one wage  That's
мы смотрим Одна работа одна ставка Вот
why For example, in Lithuania in the Czech Republic Yes, for
почему Например в Литве в Чехии Да
example, a
например
teacher earns an order of magnitude more than a
учитель получает больше на порядок чем
teacher in
учительница в
Kstovo Well, I don’t know, By
кстове Ну вот я не знаю у Мне тоже
the way, Daki is not very happy with the fact that they
кстати Даки не очень-то доволен то что
don’t get very good teaching from me, it’s
не очень уча чистя получают у меня
just a sore subject, yes, I have a mother  I
просто это больная Тема да у меня мама
worked as a teacher at school. I studied
работала учительнице в школе Я учился
at the school where my mother worked
как раз в школе в которой мама работала
and I will say this. Mom, we were always let’s say
и я скажу так Мама мы всегда были скажем
not that we were not rich, we were a poor
не то что не богатые мы были бедной
family. My mother never took
семьёй У меня мама не брала взятки
any bribes. That’s why my mother has a higher
никакие Вот и почему моя мать с высшим
education in pedagogy. Yes  should
образованием педагогическим Да должна
have existed like this and now
была так существовать и вот сейчас
because when you said I’m 60,000 yes there’s
потому что вы когда сказали Я 60.000 да
no such rate It’s just
ставки такой нету Просто это
necessary it’s necessary to come it’s necessary to
надо это надо приходить это надо
come at 6 8 am in and leave 8
приходить в 6 8 утра в и уходить 8
not they GTO leave there well hours Well hours
не они ГТО уходят там ну часов Ну часов
Yes she’s leaving don’t look e  still at home and still at
Да уходит она не смотри е ещё дома и ещё
home checking then the notebook isn’t there, well,
дома проверяет тогда тетрадь нет ну она
they’re checking it there like Wait,
они по там проверяют это как Подожди
look if if 4 hours one rate and 4
Смотри если если 4 часа одну ставку и 4
hours the second it’s only class
часа второе это уже только классных
lessons 8 hours This is with mi Po plus in already
занятий 8 часов Это с ми По плюс во уже
like 4 and with breaks And so  then it’s
типа 4 а с перерывами И так дальше это
unrealistic for me, my mother, I was, I
нереально у меня ж мама я же было я
grew up in fact at school, my mother took me, I
вырос по сути в школе меня мама брала я
came to after-school school. Yes, when the after-school program
приходил на продлёнку Да когда продлёнка
ended in the lower grades, and I sat
заканчивалась в младших классах И сидел
in the back of my mother’s lot, doing homework while my
на задне парти у мамы делал уроки пока
mother told the high school students. Uh-huh.
мама рассказывал старшеклассником
It’s so simple. Why 4
Угу Это так просто Да что 4
hours Well, this is such a difficult job of a
часа Ну это такая непростая работа
teacher I’m aware Well, the question is
учителя Я в курсе Ну так вот вопрос
why, for example, here I am now, yes I am a
почему например вот сри я сейчас да Я
university teacher in Sacramento
преподаватель университетов Сакраменто
Yes, I teach anthropology That’s why
Да я преподаю антропологию Вот почему у
my salary is 99,000 dollars, which in
меня зарплата 99.000 долларов это по
our Russian language is 900,000 rubles,
нашему российскому 900.000 руб
and I think it’s also
получается да и я считаю ещё это
small  salary Yes, there are more
маленькая зарплата Да есть больше
salaries in our field, and my mother, a
зарплаты в нашей сфере а моя мама
teacher, received such a meager
учительница получала такую мизерную
salary. That’s why
зарплату Вот почему так ну не очень
work was not very valued. Yes, this is not very good in our country either. I
ценился труд Да у нас это тоже не очень
think that the work of a teacher is not valued; it is
хорошо считаю что не ценится труд
not highly valued. Why is it that in
учителя не высоко ценится А почему вот в
Russia a teacher like this  he,
России учитель и этот как он
uh, a doctor,
эээ медик так мало
gets paid so little Well, I honestly don’t know
получают Ну я честно говор Не знаю
why there’s so
почему так
little gold gas diamonds oil We
мало золото газ алмазы нефть Всё у нас
have everything and people live
есть а люди живут
poorly, why Well, it’s time for people to live, [ __ ], well,
бедно почему Ну люди пора живут гово ну
wait, stop, if we take for example
Подождите стоп если мы возьмём например
some kind of Iraq, the same is
какой-то там Ирак так же самое есть
who  - someone who lives richly, some kind of
кто-то кто живёт богато какой-то Да
tycoon, and the general population is poor, and so it is
Магнат а основное население бедно так и
with us. Yes, of course, there is someone who
у нас Да конечно кто-то есть
gets out And so on, but he can’t even
выкручивается И так дальше но он доже
plow like that for me,
пахать вот так мне просто батя вот у
my dad, my dad, he speaks like this for Putin,
меня батя он за Путина такой говорит вот
America wants to  for I brought him, yes, my
Америка хочет на за я его привёз да гою
dad, come, they issued a visa for him Yes, he
батя Прилетай оформили визу ему Да он
arrived, no, it’s not like that,
прилетел посмотрел нет у вас всё не так
in short, it’s not like that, he’s seen enough of those
это короче не так вот он те насмотрелся
and he lives very well, if he lives in
и он живёт оче тек если он живёт в
the country, he sees how they live, he tells
стране видит как живут он рассказывает
you, Look, don’t look, look
ва по Смотри не вот смотрите вот
look, you know how
смотрите вот знаете как вот как человек
happy a person is, dissatisfied with life. Why, not because of
доволен недоволен жизнью От чего не от
how he is, to be honest, even
того что как он честно говоря даже
more so, not because of how he lives at the
больше не от того как он живёт в данный
moment, but because of the dynamics that are going on,
момент а от того какая динамика идёт вот
if, roughly speaking, T person lives not
если грубо говоря живёт Т человек не
very richly Yes,  if he sees that
очень богато Да вот если видит что жизнь
his life is improving every year,
у него с каждым годом
even if he does not live very richly,
улучшается пусть даже он не очень богато
but he sees that every year his life is
жит но он видит что с каждым годом жи
becoming better for him, then he will be satisfied with
становится него луше то он будет доволен
life, but if, on the contrary, even his person is
жизнь а если наоборот даже е чело
satisfied with God, every year it becomes
довольно Бога с каждым годом становится
worse and worse, he will be  not very happy, you
хуже и хуже он будет не очень доволен жи
know, the EU person, if a person I see
понимаете ЕС чело если человек я вижу
there, I understand that there in Russia they are
там я понимаю что там у нас в России там
not very rich, not the richest, but not
не очень богаты не самые богатые но не
the poorest, of course, but not the richest, I
самые бедные конечно но не самые богатые
see it, BC early, VM SJ,
есть это вижу ВС рано ВМ СЖ
and for me there is a prospect for
есть и для меня есть перспектива для
there is a prospect for my children in this country, it’s
моих детей в этой стране есть
cool that I’m living, that I
перспектива прикольно что я живу что я
’ll be in a year, in two years, in 10
буду чере через год через два через 10
years, I’ll be better off than I’m living now. It
лет буду жи чем лучше чем я сейчас живу
seems to me that of those sanctions
де Мне кажется что из тех санкций
that were imposed on Russia, why and
которые наложили на Россию с чего а
then from the 2nd Yes, no  everything is already so
потом с 2 второго Да не всё так уже
rosy What is the dynamics? Look at
радужно стоит Какая динамика Посмотрите
the dynamics of prices and the dynamics of wages, it’s generally
динамику цен и динамику зарплат вообще
unpleasant, on the
неприятно
contrary, by the way, by the
правда наоборот кстати кстати вот у нас
way, that’s why inflation is now accelerating in our country, that
поэтому сейчас разгоняется инфляцию что
our wage dynamics are higher than the
у нас динамика зарплат выше чем динамика
price dynamics, so now, seriously, why
цен поэтому сейчас уу серьёзно с чего да
yes, the key rate? Well, the key rate is increasing,
ключевую Ну ключевую ставку пот повышает
what?  we just, well, salaries
что у нас просто ну зарплаты сильно
have increased significantly compared to prices
выросли по сравнению с ценами ключевую
key rate What is the Key Rate Well, what is
ставку Что такое Ключевая ставка Ну это
your name there, what is the
у вас как у вас там как называется
Key Rate called interest
Ключевая ставка interest
Rate Well, yes, well, we have the right name for the refinancing rate
Rate Ну да ну у нас как ставка
Yes, it turns out to be
правильно Да это получается к
m more Key Rate those  worse, it
м больше Ключевая ставка тем хуже это
just shows that there is
как раз показывает что в экономике
huge inflation in the economy no it is no that
инфляция огромнейшая нет это нет что
inflation Yes because it is
инфляция Да потому что
accelerating
разгоняется
it is just the opposite when
это так это как раз наоборот когда
wages are worse
зарплаты да хуже
than
чем идёт разгон
inflation is accelerating when in short you have in Russia The
инфляции когда короче у вас в России
key rate is rising is it good
Ключевая ставка повышается это хорошо
or bad from good or from  bad not
или плохо от хорошего или от плохого не
very bad no no T to contain inflation
очень нет нет Т чтобы сдержать инфляцию
to contain
чтобы сдержать
[music]
[музыка]
inflation and what is holding back increased
инфляцию и что сдерживает повысили
first 18 19 20 and further They say they will
сначала 18 19 20 и дальше Говорят будут
increase I don’t know how it will not be
повышать не знаю так как будет не будет
now
сейчас
with How much is it now 20 or
с Сколько уже сейчас 20 или
22 to be honest I don’t know I don’t care  the
22 честно говоря не знаю не смот Дело в
fact is that with such a key rate it’s already
том что при такой ключевой ставки уже
pointless to take out loans Yes, that’s
кредиты брать бессмысленно Да уже
all And why do we need loans for I
всё А зачем нам кредиты нужно
don’t want to for what for what
по не хочу чтобы бы для чего для чего
Credit Why the key rate in general
Креди Для чего ключевую ставку вообще
Why do people take loans
Для чего люди берут кредиты
not about such loans in general enterprise
не про такие вобще кредиты предприятие
Yes he needs an
Да ему нужно
extension who  who
расширение кто воз
20 so the
20 так
work of Tiya which are strategic
работа Тия которые стратегические
which you see we don’t Well, what are the
которые нужны видите нам не Ну что есть
key ones such chetical
ключевые такие ческие
they don’t take farms there well
они не берут фермерские хозяйств там ну
agricultural enterprises they don’t take there for
сельхозпредприятия они не берут там по
such there Gru at 25% of the loan they are
такие там Гру по 25% кредита их
subsidized by the state they are given a
субсидирует государство им дают под
loan at 3% by the state here  now there is a
кредит по 3% государство вот сейчас на
war going on Show
идёт вое Покажи кредиты
defense loans llo Show where in Russia
обороны лло Покажи где в России кредиты
there are loans at 3% Show me for real, it’s interesting that there
по 3% есть Покажи реально вот Интересно
are such agricultural loans Find where the loans are
есть такие сельхоз Найди где кредиты Вот
Show me for real how many of these
покажи это реально сколько таких
loans at 3% were issued last year,
кредитов по 3% выдано вот в прошлом году
look at me, look at me, look here
у меня смотрите вот у меня смотрите вот
I have a mortgage on my house Yes, it’s taken
у меня вот дом напер ипотеку Да взят
Find it again Find it Look Let’s answer
Найди ещё раз Найди смотри Давай ответь
for your words No answer Find it
за свои слова нет ответь Вот найди
now Really if there are such loans
сейчас реально если есть такие кредиты
How many of these loans were issued last
сколько таких кредитов выдано за прошлый
year in what volume I’m interested, well
год на какой объём Мне же интересно ну
now I won’t I won’t I won’t  just
сейчас я не буду не я не буду просто
look for these statistics now. I just
сейчас искать эту статистику Просто я
know there are programs like that, there are programs
знаю есть программы такие есть программы
now, well, let’s not find it yet, find it, no,
сейчас ну давай пока не найди найди не
no, if there is such a program, Find it, I
нет Если есть такая программа Найди не я
won’t tell you, I’ll find it now, wait,
вам не буду я сейчас найду подожди
look, I’ll
смотри я сейчас
find it now. Find, you can see agriculture at 3%
Найдите видно сельское хозяйство по 3%
[music]
[музыка]
find  I feel
найдите мне
like this
такое
Now maybe once there was something like this
Сейчас может когда-то что-то такое
Show me on what
было Покажите мне на каком ба какой сайт
bank website offers such a loan for a
банка предлагает такой кредит для
farmer
фермера
because maybe this is not this is not this you know
так как может это не это не это знаете
this is a government program This is not a ban yes yes Well
это идёт госпрограмма Это же не бан да
find it Yes it’s all the same
да Ну найдите Да вот всё равно же банк
Some bank is issuing Yes, according to the state program,
какой-то выдаёт Да по госпрограмме
some bank is giving a loan, find me on the
какой-то банк даёт кредит найдите мне на
website of some bank that
сайте какого-то банка что действительно
there really is such a program working maybe now
есть такая программа работающая может
no now I know what they were giving Now
сечас нет сечас Я знаю что давали Сейчас
maybe 3% I don’t know how much
может бы по 3% Я не знаю под Сколько
you are giving now  They confirmed that there is 3% each and no, no, no,
дают вы утвердили что есть по 3% и не ну
no, no, before that, I know
не Не ну это не нет до этого было я знаю
that they gave 3%, but for example,
что по 3% давали но у меня например вот
look at mine, well, acquaintances,
смотрите у меня вот э Ну знакомые
acquaintances, let's not forget about tales about
знакомый Давайте не без сказок про
acquaintances, just really real, no,
знакомых вот просто реально реальный не
no  I’m not I’m not saying they’re not in
не я не я не говорю они не сельским
agriculture they took on Yes yes yes let’s
хозяйством они взяли по Да да да давайте
now but I have it Look don’t give me
сечас но у меня ите Смотри мне не давай
about the mortgage I’ll ask you later and we’ll
про ипотеку я потом тебя спрошу и мы
look Find it now Yes that’s really about
поищем Найдите сейчас Да вот реально про
farming you said you confidently
фермерские вы сказали вы уверенно так
said so yes I’m saying  you took me to show off,
говорили да я говорю вы На понт меня
I checked. Let's now
брали я проверил Давайте теперь вы
prove
докажите
what I have to tell you. Well, what
тогда что я должен сказать вам Ну что
is it that really interests me, maybe
такое действительно мне интересно может
I'm wrong? No, what can I prove to you? I'm not a
я не прав Нет ну что вам доказать я не
gender. Well, find out that there is some kind of bank Yes,
пол Ну найдите что есть какой-то банк Да
which offers this one for the farmer
который предлагает для фермера вот этот
preferential loan 3%
льготный кредит 3%
Well, now I’m saying now, most likely not
Ну сейчас говорю сейчас скорее всего не
3% now maybe there and 5% here Find
3% сейчас может там и 5% вот Найдите
find and Say yes Say Find for
найдите и Скажите да Скажите Найдите на
five Go for 5% Say yes I was mistaken
пять Зайдите на 5% Скажите да я ошибся
Here are five current there is
Вот пять действующая есть
that’s all
такая всё
[music]
[музыка]
let’s see this
посмотрим так
Kai So this is what we have here, I’m just looking at
Кай Так это что у нас вот просто смотрю
the Ministry The Ministry is not not
Министерство Министерство не не
the Ministry
Министерство
that’s stop not the Ministry is not news And
вот стоп не Министерство не новости А
specifically Specifically that the bank you have
конкретно Конкретно что банк-то вки вы
such a program is in effect not
такая программа есть действует не
news that the Ministry is planning No, well,
новости что Министерство планирует Не ну
there is a department of preferential lending,
вот есть отдел льготного кредитования
there is  The Ministry is a state program of
вот есть Министерство это госпрограмма
understanding department tno where you are,
понима отдел тно кда вот пожалуйста вот
look here again I
смотрите вот вот ещё раз я ещё раз
repeat again bank Show me the bank where I can
повторяю банк Покажи мне банк где я могу
get like a Farmer yes such a loan everything
взять как Фермер да такой кредит всё
else news Ministry light bulbs
остальное новости Министерство лампочки
ko understand these are not commercial banks you
ко понимаете это не коммерческие банки
understand once again The Ministry does not issue
понимаете ещё раз Министерство не выдаёт
loans  Yes, anyway, the state
кредиты Да всё равно государство выдаёт
even issues loans through a bank through a
даже кредиты через банк через
state bank, it’s not the bank itself that
государственный банк не сам банк не
can’t give, you know, it’s not the bank itself, you
может дать понимаете Не он сам банк
know, the bank is there, it gives, for example,
понимаете там идёт банк даёт например
you know how the program
там знаете как программа
works if you don’t know Tell me how
действует если не в курсе Расскажите как
it works Well, if I don’t know
это действует Ну вот если я если не в
desa, if you go under this program,
курсе деса если идёт под эту программу
you take from stop stop stop don’t
вы берёте с стоп стоп стоп не
put off the phone you’ll
откладывайте телефон вы сейчас будете
continue to look now Let’s Well, well Who gives
дальше искать Давайте Ну ну Кто выдаёт
money Who gives money to the farmer no no they
деньги Кто фермеру выдаёт деньги не нет
give the farmer Credit to loans
фермеру выдают Креди к кредиты
commercial banks the bank everything is ba and the
коммерческие банки банк всё ба а
state is right here Wait,
государство правильно вот Подождите вот
look it’s working  look, the bank is
смотрите действует смотрите идёт банк
coming there, not roughly speaking, look, it’s going
идёт там не грубо говоря смотрите идёт
there at 20%, so it issues a loan at
там под 20% так так выдаёт кредит под
20% And according to this program, for example,
20% А по этой программе за него например
part of the interest is paid off by the state.
часть процентов гасит государство Вот
Show me, he gets his 20 if he
покажи ба получает свои 20 если он
gives out 20% at a time, he gets 20% Look,
выдаёт по 20% он получает 20% Вот смотри
don’t show show So that on the bank’s website
не покажи покажи Вот чтоб на сайте банка
there is this announcement on the bank’s website
есть вот это объявление на сайте банка
that issues this here bank bank it’s
который такое выдаёт тут банк банк он
here yet No again just a bank Yes
вот ещё Нет ещё раз как раз банк Да
because such programs Yes operate
потому что такие программы Да действуют
only through a connection If not only
только через подклю Если не есть только
through certain banks Yes here it is
через определённые банки Да вот и
uh, according to a certain compensation scheme Yes, and the
ээ по определённой схеме возмещения Да и
bank says it right away Yes we have
банк сразу это говорит Да у нас есть
such a program Yes we can do this
такая программа Да мы можем это делать
Find me at least one bank Well, now we
Найди мне хоть один банк Ну да сейчас
’ll see, I’ll give you another minute, come on,
так посмотрим даю тебе ещё минуту давай
look here Sberbank Here you go,
вот смотри вот Сбербанк Вот идт вот
look at preferential lending to the
смотрите льготное кредитование
agro-industrial complex financing of the current  activity, the
АПК финансирование текущей деятельности
loan term is up to 12 months, the
срок действия кредита до 12 месяцев
minimum rate is 1% per annum already and there is one
минимальная ставка 1% годовых уже и один
Chuchu
Чучу
rouge Well, you see that I don’t see what
руже Ну вот Вот видите что я не вижу что
you are showing there 1% Yes, come on, find what
ты там показываешь 1% Да давай найди что
you already have without interest,
вообще бе без процента есть уже у тебя
through
через
here I found the minimum rate  rate
вот нашёл вот ставка минимальная ставка
1% per annum maximum rate plus 2% per
1% годовых максимальная ставка плюс 2%
annum i.e. 1 billion rubles within the
годовых о то есть 1 млр руб в пределах
maximum limits of the constituent entities of the
максимальных лимитов субъектов
Russian Federation specifics of lending, the
РФ особенности кредитования договор о
financing agreement is signed After the
финансировании подписывается После
application is approved by the Ministry of Agriculture, the period for
согласования заявки с михом
consideration of the application by the Ministry of Agriculture
срок рассмотрения заявки минсельхозом
of Russia is up to seven working days, the period of
России до семи рабочих дней срок
validity of the approval is calendar days,
действия согласования календарных дней
so e  You already, that is, you had
так что е Ты уже да то есть у тебя было
3% Now you found 1D in short you
3% Теперь ты нашёл 1Д короче там
show it there Yes, I didn’t tell you 3% I
показываешь Да вам не сказал 3% Я
told you about 3% so look
примерно сказал по 3% тебе так смотри
it’s shorter, it became 1.2% It’s already
оно короче уменьшили стало 1.2% Уже
become Yes, maybe you’ll find more for
стало Да может ещё по ещ найдёшь
free in general And also  and it’s just not
бесплатно вообще А ещё и просто не то
that the loan is shorter, interest-free And they also
что кредит короче беспроцентный А ещё и
give you a billion dollars for free Well, you didn’t
деньги дают даром миллиард Ну тебе не
like what I found Yes,
понравилось что я нашёл Да
I don’t understand what you found Did you find
Я не понимаю что ты нашёл Ты какую нашл
some news again And so on And
снова какие-то новости И так дальше И
so on Well, I understand,
так дальше Ну я понял ты
just tell me  Balabol Yes, because where
просто скажи ты Балабол Да пото что куда
Hey
Эй
al that's
ал вот и
all the letter on my Ista I don't know what this is for
всё пись на мий Иста Я не знаю для чего
Why are you marveling at
це тоб Для чего тоб там дивитись на о
my face Ale for you one two or three
мий фейс Але для тебе один два або три
clicks Ale ti trimae me and I will lick
клика Але ти тримае мене и я буду лизати
Wow in me there  Kupa flower and in me there will be a
Вау в мене там Купа фловер и в мене буде
great mood sob robiti Novi cool
класний настрой щоб робити Нови крути
video caption on my Instagram pop
видео пидпись на мий Instagram попк
Andriy Oh
Андрий О
so let me
так давай я тебя
check for you and
чекаю а